<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A general epistle to friends everywhere who have received, believe and know the truth of God as it is in Jesus.</title>
            <title>General epistle to friends every where.</title>
            <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216935</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828648</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828648</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33079</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56017)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33079)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1931:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A general epistle to friends everywhere who have received, believe and know the truth of God as it is in Jesus.</title>
                  <title>General epistle to friends every where.</title>
                  <author>Parke, James, 1636-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: Horsleydown the 24th. of 5th. month, 1687. James Parke.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Quakers --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:33079:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:33079:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33079:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A General EPISTLE TO FRIENDS EVERY WHERE, Who have Received, Believe and know the Truth of GOD as it is in JESUS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Jeſus anſwered, Are there not Twelve Hours in the Day? If a man walk in the Day, he ſtumbleth not, becauſe he ſeeth the Light of this World.</p>
                  <p>But if a man walk in the Night, he ſtumbleth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <bibl>John 11. 9, 10.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <opener>
               <salute>Dear Friends and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHo are made partakers with us of Salvation, and Life, and Peace with God through Jeſus Chriſt, in perilous Times, and have been made willing to take part with the Saints through believing in him, and have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for His Names ſake, and in patience poſſeſſed your Souls, as a People filled and furniſhed with power from on High to do the will of God, and finiſh that work he hath given you to do in your day and Generation; my dear love in the heavenly ſence of that Salvation, Life and Peace which we have received from God through Chriſt Jeſus the Prince of Peace, dearly ſalutes you all
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33079:3"/>
every where, who patiently have given your backs to the Smiter, and in the will of God have ſuffered Joyfully for well-doing, and have not ſainted, nor been weary, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> removed, nor been ſhaken in mind, when long furrows were plowed upon your backs, but in Patience and Long-ſuffering endured and came through great tribulations for Righteouſneſs ſake; the goodneſs of God in helping, ſaving and delivering of us in the time of need, is evermore to be minded, and never to be forgotten, but greatly prized by us all who have been and are preſerved living Witneſſes of the ſame, to our abundant joy and comfort, when things looked moſt black and diſmal without. O what Reſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment and conſolation have a Remnant felt and experienced, when others were amazed, tormented and ſurprized with ſudden fears to behold their expectations fruſtrated, and their hopes periſh, your hope was in the Lord, and your confidence in him that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fails them that hope in his mercy, and put their truſt in him. And the Lord hath kept you in this Day of Tryal and Hour of Temptation, as a quiet Habitation, and as a Tabernacle that ſhall not be deſtroyed, nor one ſtake thereof removed, for all the ſhaking of the Mountains, and the Earth, and Heavens that have been, and will be more and more, to make way for that which cannot be ſhaken or removed, but ſhall ſtand for ever; and how doth all things work together for good to them that dwell in the love of God and Chriſt Jeſus; above all, in this day of ſhaking of all falſe Foundations, and all who have built thereupon. How are the ſhaken in mind, they have ſtumbled and faln, and ſeem to have none to help them up, their minds being from the only Helper Chriſt Jeſus, the tried Stone, Elect and precious, who is laid in Sion for a Foundation on which the Church of God is built, <hi>and which the gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt;</hi> and this Foundation of God it ſtands ſure; and all who are thereupon kept and preſerved; they are as <hi>Mount Sion that cannot be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved,</hi> by all the ſhakings of the winds that ariſe; Floods that come, or the Rains that fall, becauſe they are built upon this Rock <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> which is immovable, who hath been and is our Rock and Reſuge to this day, Glory to the Lord God for ever, who hath gathered a Remnant to himſelf out of the World, and the wickedneſs of it; and hath brought out from the barren Mountains, to the Mountain of his Houſe, even the Mountain of Holineſs, where his hand appears and is ſeen to work and bring mighty things to paſs for and in the behalf of his choſen Heritage,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33079:3"/>
whom the Lord greatly delights in, and taketh pleaſure in doing good unto. Now this Mountain of the Lord's Houſe ſhall be eſtabliſhed on the top of the Mountains, and ſhall be exalted above the Hills, how high and ſtrong ſoever they may appear; that are as Mountains lifted up or ariſe againſt the Mountain of the Lords Houſe; or is of another nature, and contrary thereunto, they muſt all be brought down and laid waſt in man and woman before the Mountain of the Lord can be eſtabliſhed in them and exalted above the Hills, which Chriſt Jeſus ſaid muſt be laid low before the Lord alone be exalted. And <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaw a little Stone cut out of the Mountain without hands, that ſhould fill the whole Earth; here was no Crafts-man or cunning Artiſts hands at work in cutting out this little Stone, cut out of the Mountain it was without hands; no wit or power of man could do it, but only through the Wiſdom of God and his inviſible power, for with God all things are poſſible: he can make a little Stone cut out of the Mountain fill the whole Earth; he can make a little one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſtrong Nation. Now, Dear Friends, feel the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe eſtabliſhed on the the top of that which is of the Houſe of <hi>Eſau,</hi> which muſt be as ſtubble, and feel the Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> faln; and the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> that was faln down, raiſed up in you, and that every breach thereof may be healed, that the enemy hath made at any time to the weakning or the throwing of it down; and when any falls into ſin or commits iniquity that makes a breach upon the Tabernacle of <hi>David,</hi> wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens the good in them: ſo then the bad Houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> grows ſtronger, and wickedneſs increaſeth in ſuch to a great height. O how many Mountains and Hills within and without, hath the Lord our God already brought down and laid waſt, that he might ſet his King upon his Holy Hill of Sion, and declare his decree that ſhall ſtand, notwithſtanding what man or men may decree contrary. God will accompliſh the thoughts of his heart, and will bring to paſs his Act, his ſtrange Act, what he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and purpoſeth to do in and for his undefiled Remnant: he will effect it; it ſhall come to paſs; not a Jot or little ſhall fail till all be fulfilled. So, dear Friends, feel <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> ſet upon his <hi>Holy Hill of Sion,</hi> who ſhall Reign for ever and ever, and ſit upon the <hi>Throne of Majeſty on High;</hi> I ſay, in the Name of the Lord God witneſs his Reign and him to ſway the Scepter of Righteouſneſs in you, till every thing that is contrary to him, or that would exalt it ſelf againſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33079:4"/>
his Government, be brought into obedience and ſubjection there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that nothing may Rule or Reign but his bleſſed Life and Power in and over all for evermore; and that he may be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in you all, who is worthy of Glory, Honour, and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, feel and witneſs him come with power and great glory, and taking to himſelf his great power, whereby you will all know every Valley exalted, and every Mountain and Hill laid low, that would lift up it ſelf to oppoſe or hinder the work of the Lord, or would not the Lord ſhould Reign, and all keep ſenſible of that day, wherein the Lord alone ſhall be exalted, and when all fleſh ſhall tremble before him, who layeth low the loftineſs of man. What is any Mountain, or all Nations before him, when he cometh in Triumph, <hi>Skipping over the Mountains, and leaping over the Hills;</hi> of oppoſition within and without, when he makes his power known; how doth he ſhake the Earth, and cauſe the keepers of the Houſe to tremble, and how will he puniſh that <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viathan,</hi> the crooked Serpent, whoſe way is in the Sea, that long hath deceived the Nations, and cauſed People to wonder after the Beaſt, and to ſay, <hi>Who is like unto the Beaſt,</hi> or, <hi>Who can make War with him;</hi> and maketh many for an hour to give their power to the Beaſt that is to be ſlain, and with him the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and given to the burning Flame in the day of the Lord, <hi>that burns as an Oven;</hi> and all that are proud, and all that do wickedly ſhall be as ſtubble; the day cometh that ſhall burn them up, and neither leave of them Root or Branch. All, Dear Friends, keep in the fear of the Lord, and think upon his Name; <hi>But fear not man whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils; neither fear what man can do,</hi> Profeſſor or Profane, if they ſet themſelves in a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced mind and Spirit againſt you, <hi>Speaking all manner of evil againſt you for the Name of Chriſt,</hi> which you know and believe in; fear you not their fears, neither be any of you afraid of their Revilings, <hi>Whom the Moth ſhall eat like a Canker, and the Wind ſhall drive away as ſtubble.</hi> How hath the hearts of many failed them for fear? And what great fearfulneſs hath ſurprized the Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites of this Revolting and Backſliding Age, that have not been able to dwell with devouring Fire, or ſtand when the Lord appear? <hi>Who ſits as a Reſiner with Fire to purge away the droſs, and take away all the Tin; and who cometh with his Fan in his hand, thoroughly to purge his Flowre, and gather his Wheat into his Garner,</hi> where he will keep and preſerve it ſafe, and ſecure it from that that would eat it up and deſtroy it where ever that appears, you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33079:4"/>
who are of God, if never ſo little you are the Lords gathered Wheat into his Garner, and who are not gathered to God, nor born of God, they are the Chaff, they are the Children of the wicked One, and will do wickedly, being void of a Divine or heavenly underſtanding, how wiſe ſoever they may be to do evil, and they are in the ſight of the Lord, but a heap of confuſion and corruption, although their Mountain ſeem to be never ſo great and high, the Lord can and will lay it low, and make it a Plain when he pleaſeth, and by what way and method he pleaſeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So feel the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe eſtabliſhed on the top of the Mountain, the Mountain of Holineſs, and the Holy Hill of Sion; feel over all unholy Mountains of ſin and corruption, and God's Holy Hill over all the unholy Hills that are got up in the fall. That, dear Friends, you all may live, move and keep your Habitation in Chriſt Jeſus, that Noble Vine, into which you were grafted, that never fell but liveth and abideth for ever, who is your Rock and Foundation, your Buckler, Shield, and mighty Defence; when the Winds blow, Rains fall, and the Floods of the Ungodly come forth, as if they would overflow the Banks; you know who hath power over the Winds, the Rain, and the raging Sea, ſtedfaſtly believe in him Chriſt Jeſus, and let your hearts be fixed, truſting in the Lord's great power, however it be in the World, as to Troubles, Amazements, and Fears. In Chriſt Jeſus, the Prince of Peace, feel a conſtant Peace, that his Peace may remain with you, and he may guide you continually, and then your Reſt alſo will be glorious in him, and patience will poſſeſs your Souls in the greateſt Tribulation that can come; and you will have Joy and Conſolation, when the Faces of many ſhall gather paleneſs, and fear and aſtoniſhment ſhall ſeize and take hold upon others, becauſe of the fearſul Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that will come upon them, due to them for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and great abominations.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Dear Friends,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THerefore be all <hi>diligent to make your Calling and Election ſo ſure</hi> and certain, that you conſtantly may have the freſh renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the Spirit of God, and that to bear you witneſs that you are of the few or ſmall number who are ſaved, that enter the ſtrait Gate, and walketh in the narrow way that leadeth unto
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33079:5"/>
Life Eternal, which but few find, and ſuch as never yet found it, how ſhould they walk in it; and you that have found it, keep low walking in it, and let none of your hearts by any means be lifted up, by any thing you do for the truth, or with any thing that you enjoy from God, <hi>Who is the giver of every good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Gift,</hi> whether Temporal or Spiritual; but ſtill keep your hearts and minds unto God, and in perfect love unto him above all, in the pure enjoyment of all the mercies, which you have received from him; let not the things of this world have place in your hearts again, who have been gathered to God out of the World; for whoſoever let their minds and affections after that which is earthly, ſuch cannot well affect heavenly things; therefore all have great need, even as much as ever, to keep your hearts with all diligence, that the enemy of the Soul and deſtroyer enter not again, where he once was caſt out by Chriſt Jeſus; <hi>O watch and pray that you enter not into temptation,</hi> when you are tempted to evil; in the hour of temptation watch in the word of God's patience; be ſure that you keep that hid in your hearts, and take heed to it, and you will witneſs it a Light to your Feet, to lead and keep you all from the Temptations of Satan to Sin and Evil, which you may expect to meet with now, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho it be a time of eaſe, as from outward Sufferings, for that may expoſe you more to the aſſaults of Satan inwardly, that now by his Agents he cannot impriſon your Bodies, fine you, nor ſpoil your Goods, for meeting together to worſhip God, he will beſet you and aſſault you now another way, to wit, within, there to work, if a diligent conſtant watch be not kept in the fear of the Lord; ſuch will be in danger to be enſnared: you know many of you that the enemy hath many ſnares, and when he cannot catch in one he will lay another more privily to catch the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent in, to enſnare ſuch as be of an upright Converſation. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not any of you, that by the Lord's Holy Spirit and Power have known your Souls, to be quickened, ſuffer death to enter or prevail again, ſo to cauſe the ſecond death to have power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver you, or to be twice dead and pluck'd up by the roots; how can any good Fruit be expected from ſuch Trees, but an utter withering. But, my dear Friends, in this time of freedom and outward liberty, feel the juſt and holy One at liberty, and to have freedom in all your hearts, that there the juſt may not ſuffer by the unjuſt, for that vexeth and grieveth the Holy Spirit, when any go into that which is evil, and commit iniquity in the ſight
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33079:5"/>
of the Lord that quencheth the Spirit of God, 'tis all out of the Truth and judged by it, and ſtill all is to keep down to that which judgeth down the evil in its firſt motion in the heart or appearance there; then it will not get place to have dominion; but you will all in the Name and Power of the Lord have dominion over, and Reign over that which is evil, which formerly Ruled in your mortal Bodies to the diſhonour of God.</p>
               <p>And Friends, Let all beware of Covetouſneſs, which is Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. Let not any of you covet an evil Coveteouſneſs to your Houſe, or to ſet your Neſts on High; and keep out of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frauding, cunning over reaching of one another, or any which you are concern'd in Trade, or otherwiſe with. Oppreſs not the Poor; wrong no man, but give unto all that which is their due, without grudging. Avoid diſhoneſt Gain, or making craſty advantages of any perſon to make your Families Great or Rich in the World. Neither let your hearts be lifted up when you ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the World in abundance; conſider you are but as Stewards of it for a little time, and muſt give an Account to the creator of all things how you uſe it, or what good or hurt you have done with it, or by it, daily take a view of the uncertainty of all viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things; and why ſomtime they are given to the owners thereof to their hurt; for its not that in themſelves they are hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but becauſe many times they are ill uſed or abuſed, but at the beſt not to be truſted in: therefore 'tis better to be Rich in ſaith and rich in good Works, whilſt we abide here in this earthly Tabernacle, for every good Tree brings forth good Fruit, although the evil Tree bring forth the corrupt evil Fruit, therefore all that profeſs Repentance towards God and Faith in Chriſt Jeſus ought to bring forth good Fruit, <hi>even Fruit meet for Repentance, whereby our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father may be Glorified,</hi> and we may be Recorded in the Book of Life; as thoſe that are preſerved good and faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to God in our Generation; that have paſs'd the time of our Sojourning here in the fear of God, and finiſhed our courſe with Joy, unto whom an everlaſting Crown and Kingdom is prepared and will be given, to poſſeſs and inherit unto all Eternity. O what will a profeſſion of God and knowledg of his Will avail any that are not faithful to God in what he hath ſhewed them to be his Will: Will it not tend to their greater Condemnation? Will it not add to their wo and miſery in the day of Judgment, or when Chriſt ſhall enter into Judgment with them, and not only Judge Peoples words and works, but as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>He ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33079:6"/>
Judge the ſecrets of all mens Hearts; He ſearcheth the Heart and trieth the Reins.</hi> 'Twill be in vain to ſeek to hide or cover any ſin and evil from him that will ſearch and find out all the hidden works of darkneſs and diſhoneſty which any would hide or cover from the Lord, who ſeeth all, and will aſſuredly reward every man according to his works, ſuch as every one ſoweth, ſuch muſt they Reap; <hi>He that ſoweth to the Fleſh, of the Fleſh ſhall Reap corruption, but he that ſoweth to the Spirit, of the Spirit ſhall reap Life Everlaſting;</hi> it is certainly a fearful and dangerous thing to fall into the hands of the living God, for diſobedience to his Will, <hi>and holding the Truth in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi> for to know God, and not to glorifie him as God, nor to walk in obedience and thankfulneſs to him for his benefits: this diſpleaſeth the Lord; and indeed this is the cauſe why ſome convinced among us, and know the Truth, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come vain in their Imaginations, whoſe fooliſh hearts is darkned, and are not obedient to what was manifeſt in them; neither are they Righteous, nor walk as becomes the precious Truth of God, but through Diſobedience and Unrighteouſneſs, diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God and his Truth, which they profeſs, cauſing the Holy and Righteous way of God to be evil ſpoken of; alſo cauſing ſome to ſtumble and take offence at the way of God, by their unfaithfulneſs and diſorderly walking, for whoſoever looks out at them were not like to be drawn nearer to Truth, but rather driven further from it, by the evil Converſation of them that obey not the Truth, but do that which is contrary. And dear Friends, you that have Families of Children or Servants, and are ſet of God over them, walk wiſely towards them, inſtructing them to fear the Lord, to hate evil and love that which is good: Teach your Children and Servants the way of God, wherein you have found peace and ſafety, that they may come to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the ſame, that you and your Families may ſerve the Lord, and walk together in his way, in which is no evil, not any thing that can corrupt any Family, People or Nation. In this way of the Lord his Bleſſing is felt and experienced, to the great ſatisfaction of all the undefiled in the way: Let not any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption or Sin have liberty, and go unreproved in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, by a fooliſh pitty or indulgence towards your Children, or negligence of them and your Servants Eternal Good and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: but keep a watchful eye and care over all in vour Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, that none get up into Pride or run out into Evil and corrupt Words; neither any evil way faſhion or work, which may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33079:6"/>
the Lord, wound their own Souls, and be your grief and ſorrow, for it will be ſo, if any in your Families, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially under a profeſſion of the Truth, do that which is evil. And you that are Parents, or Maſters of Families, and have not endeavoured to reſtrain them, how will you then be clear of them if they periſh in their Iniquity. Therefore I beſeech you who are Governours of Families, Profeſſing the Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fail not to diſcharge your duty to all in your Families, unto whom you may be inſtruments of good; be of a ready mind to warn and correct them in the love of God, when they ſpeak or do evil, then there is need for it, whether they will hear or forbear, do what you can in the Light and Spirit of God to reclaim them from the evil of their waies and doings, that they together with you may ſay and do that which is good and right in the ſight of the Lord our God; who knoweth but as you are found faithful in this needful work of Teaching your Families the way of the Lord, but that you may ſave many Souls from Death in your reſpective Families. And thus indeed and in truth you become even Saviours upon Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> through Chriſt Jeſus, who was to turn Ungodlineſs from <hi>Jacob,</hi> and who ſaves his People who look unto him, work together with him, and put their confidence in him, ſo we receive power from him to deny our ſelves, and take up our daily Croſs and follow the Lord fully, in humility and lowlineſs of mind; and by this power of the Lord ſo dwelling in it, all will be inabled to keep in ſubjection that which would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt it ſelf againſt the appearance of the Lord in you. It will bring down every high thought and vain imagination; it will make ſelf of no reputation in every particular: and Friends never had more need to mind the Light and bring their deeds to it, believe in it, and walk in it than now, when even Satan transforms himſelf into the likeneſs of an Angel of Light and Truth, and his Miniſters alſo as Miniſters of Chriſt, and as in the Light of the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, all keep and abide walking, you will ſee and be able to put a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt the Divine Light and Truth, and the likeneſs of it, howſoever transformed by the prince of Darkneſs; for by the Light of the Lord you will all ſee Light to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all the transformations of the Devil and Satan, in all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33079:7"/>
his appearances; with what fair ſhews, or under what ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretences ſoever he may appear unto you or amongſt you; the cunning Serpent is at work with his transformed likeneſſes of the heavenly things of God: let none look out at that, nor think any worſe of the Light and Truth of God, becauſe that even Satan transforms himſelf into the likeneſs of an Angel of Light; and his Angels profeſs Gods precious Truth, and talk of it with enticing words; that mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom teacheth all this. God permits, that they who are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifeſt, that all Friends may ſearch and try their waies and works, and be more confirmed upon the tried Stone, elect and precious, which God hath laid in <hi>Sion</hi> for a Foundation; and another Foundation can no man lay, than that which is already laid, which not any thing can move or overthrow, but it ſtands and remains the ſame firm Rock of Ages ſtill; upon this dear Friends, do but keep and abide, and then none of theſe things, which only is ſuffered of the Lord to come to try us, ſhall be able to move any of us from our ſtability in the Truth, Light, Life and Power of the Lord God: The Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt this invincable Rock of Ages Chriſt Jeſus, upon whom the faithful are built, a Spiritual Houſhold unto God, and are become to him a choſen Generation and a Royal Prieſt-hood, to offer up to him the Spiritual Sacrifice of Praiſe, and of a broken Heart, which is accepted of the Lord: and ſurely we who are the Children of God, and his day had never more need to be continually with God, and ſee him in the mount than now, when there is ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining from God and departure from the Faith: and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many of you are very ſenſible that the miſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity now worketh, whereby Satan ſets himſelf and Agents at work, to let and hinder the work of the Lord, and yet they cry, <hi>Lord, Lord, have not we propheſied in thy Name,</hi> &amp;c. But are workers of Iniquity, which coming to be ſeen and diſcovered by the Light of the Lord, by that alſo is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned; which lets the Saints in Light ſee over it and the miſchievous intent of ſuch workers where they come, that are workers of Iniquity, their works maniſeſt what work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men they are; unto whom the Lord will ſay, <hi>I know you not, depart from me.</hi> Now as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:33079:7"/>
                  <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe reſiſt the Truth (profeſſed by them being men of corrupt minds and ſenſual, altho they may ſtill return good Words and fair Speeches, and ſo deceive the Hearts of the ſimple, with their ſeducing Spirit, and ſowing Diſcord, Diviſion, and corrupt Seed; which I do en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you all in the love of God and care for your Souls good to beware of, and not to believe every Spirit, but try them with the Light and Spirit of God which he hath given you, whereby you may ſee and diſcern clearly, betwixt Spirit and Spirit, the true from the falſe; and the things of God from thoſe things that are contrary, which he never wrought nor ever delighted in; all which is to be denyed and ſhut out, for by the Spirit of the Lord God, none can own or joyn with that which works againſt the truth, ſcatters from it inſtead of gathering to it, or that which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of moſt Chriſtian, would lay waſte the Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of God, and ſet up fleſhly Liberty inſtead of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity. In the Name of the Lord, and with his Light and Truth, ſee and fathom over all that which is not of God, which ſhall not ſtand. And Friends, feel the Ear open that trieth words, as the Pallat taſteth Meats, that you all the Spiritual Meat may feed upon, and not upon that which periſheth or dieth of it ſelf, but that which endures to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Life at the Lord's Table; all feed upon and be filled with that, and a living Hunger will be encreaſed in you all after that which is pure more and more, to the renouncing of that which is dirty, defiled and impure, under what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or colour ſoever it may appear, or what fine dreſs or gloſs ſoever it may be preſented to you in, by ſuch as may preſume to ſpeak in the Name of the Lord amongſt you, that are not really of us, but are gon out into a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparation from us, and impoſe their diſunion and diſorder in the Church of God, in oppoſition to that wholſom U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Order which that Church maintains, and is in the practice of; which tends to preſent it to God holy and without blame before him, without ſpot or wrinkle, or any thing that defiles, works abomination, or loves and makes a Lye; all which ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Holy City, which comes down from God out of Heaven, the ſeducing Spirit is of the Enemy the Father of Lies, and leadeth from
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33079:8"/>
the Truth into Lies and Error, falſhood and deceit, and who are led by this Spirit, they forge Lies and ſpeak Lies in Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, having their Conſciences ſeared, they grow ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will'd, ſtubborn and hard-hearted, and appear hard through the deceitfulneſs of ſin that dwelleth in them; loſing the true tenderneſs and brokenneſs of heart, that for a time appeared in ſome of them, before they let in this pernicious Spirit, and gave heed to it, that liberty which now they are in, and wrangle for it, was hateful to ſome of them, whereby they corrupt one another; ſo they raiſe their mountain, and ſet their unholy mountain againſt and in oppoſition to the Lord's Holy Mountain, or the Mountain of the Lord's Houſe, which is to be eſtabliſhed a top of the Mountains and exalted above the Hills, which all Nations ſhall flow unto, not only a few Nations, but even all Nations muſt flow to and come to it; and every Mountain and Hill muſt be brought down and laid waſte, that riſeth up in oppoſition againſt the Mountain of the Lord, where in his day the Lord our God maketh to his People a Feaſt of fat things full of Marrow, and Wine upon the Lees that is well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined; <hi>Glory, Glory to God and the Lamb over all, for ever and ever.</hi> None need pine for Hunger that come to know the Houſe of the Lord and keep at his Table; there is Bread enough, Spiritual Meat, ſufficient to ſatisfie every hungry Soul, with the Water of Life, whereof all may drink, ſo that you need never thirſt more.</p>
               <p>My dear Friends, who are come hither, abide with the Lord in the Mountain of his Holineſs; keep in his Temple faithfully, ſerving of God, and as you alwaies keep there you will know there is no Night it, for the Lamb is the Light thereof, and his Servants ſhall ſerve him and worſhip him, and cry, <hi>Worthy, worthy, is the Lamb, to receive Glory, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Praiſe for ever more.</hi> But let none content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or reſt ſatisfied in the outward Court, in outward Shews, in an outward Form of Religion or Godlineſs, out of the Life and Power of God: For when the Lord cometh to Judgment, his Sentance upon them will be ſharp, who have a name to live but are dead in Treſpaſſes and in Sins. How much aſtoniſhed and perplexed will ſuch be when the Lord comes? Who ſaid, <hi>Behold I come quickly to give a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33079:8"/>
to every man according to his works.</hi> How ſad will it be with all them that have not repented them, of their wicked deeds which they have done in the Body, but where it lieth at their door ſtill; all the Wickedneſs which they have committed, which they ſhould in their day given them by the Lord, have repented of and ceaſed to do; and what great multitudes of People evidently appear in that ſad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, which calls for a Lamentation from the ſaved of the Lord, who are his choſen Flock and Heritage; and who can commiſſerate the People of this Age, that are run into ſuch wicked ungodly Practices, which undoubtedly will provoke God to Anger, and to execute his Judgments upon them with great ſeverity if they repent not. But, dear Friends you who have taſted and ſeen how good the Lord is, and have of the Water of Life and the Rock that followed; <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old fed thereupon and drank thereof more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly, that you all may be filled with that which is good, and every Soul delight it ſelf in the fatneſs of that Meat which is really Spiritual, whereby all may come to be ſtrong in the Lord, and through him may be made able to ſtand in this day as firm, true and unſhaken in mind, as ever you or any of the Saints in any Age did: that you may not be found wanting, or fail in your teſtimony for his Name in the leaſt degree; none to be weaker in Faith becauſe ſome have faln, for through unbelief they fell, who are gone from the Truth and have ſold it for that that periſheth, and ſo are broken off from their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Society of Friends in it, whatſoever they may in their carnal Reaſoning urge as occaſion given to them by any; ſo all you that are come to God the Judg of all, to have fellowſhip with God and Chriſt Jeſus, keep conſtant in the near Union and Fellowſhip of the Spirit of God, where there is no ſtumbling, nor falling away from God and his Truth; but by the Light of the Lord all will ſee and learn how precious a thing it is for Brethren to dwell together in the Unity of the Spirit of God and to keep in the Unity of the Spirit, which is the Bond of Peace. And, dear Friends love one another and all Men, even your Enemies, that deſpightfully uſed you and hated you without cauſe; do good to them and pray for them.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33079:9"/>
And Friends, All greatly prize the great mercy of the Lord God, and his marvellous kindneſs towards us, who have been long accounted as Sheep for the Salughter, that he who hath the Hearts of Kings in his hand, ſhould move in the Kings Heart that now is, to conſider our diſtreſſed ſtate; and that violence and ſpoil we were expoſed unto, through the proſecution of the Penal Laws, that now the King hath put a ſtop to, and granted liberty for all to worſhip God according as in Conſcience they think they ought, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by appears a great openneſs in moſt places of this Nation, for People to hear God's precious Truth declared, and a door of hope of the gathering in of many to the Lord God, of all Nations and People. Truly Friends, this Liberty and Eaſe from outward Sufferings, ought to be uſed in great Humility and Lowlineſs of Mind; and none ought to be puffed up with it to abuſe it, or behave themſelves any way unworthy of it, leaſt the Lord ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to deprive us of that Liberty and Peace which we now enjoy, who not long ſince were troubled on every ſide, and met with many Perils, in which the Lord was with us, and ſtood by us and ſtrengthened us by his Power; and giving us true Comfort and Peace in himſelf: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding my dear Friends and Brethren, who have received from God more peculiar Gifts, for the work of the Miniſtry, for the edifying of the Body of Chriſt, and the perfecting of the Saints in Light: let the ſurtherance of the Goſpel be every one of your chief care and induſtry. Now is an open door, the Harveſt truly is great, and faithful Labourers are but few; <hi>Therefore pray ye the Lord God of the Harveſt, to ſend forth more faithful Labourers into his Harveſt,</hi> that every one returning may bring their precious Sheaves with you, and daily Exhort, Reprove, and Rebuke, with all long Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering and Patience; and be diligent in feeding the Flock and Lambs of Chriſt, over whom the Holy Ghoſt hath made you Overſeers: that altho many of you be poor in this World, yet you may be rich in Faith, and rich in the Work of the Goſpel, making many Rich with durable Riches, where you travel or are ſet for the defence of the Goſpel. And conſider and have regard one to another in your ſeveral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices for the Lord; keep ſingly and alone to God's Divine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33079:9"/>
Gift, that is in you and given you of God; and go forth in that in your Warfare, againſt what is contrary to God, none to be ſo entangled with the Affairs of this World, as to let or with-hold you from following the Lord in his Work and Service; walking uprightly and without blame in the fear of the Lord God, whoſe Servants you are, and unto whom we all ought ſingly to be given up in pure Obedience: And all Friends every where keep up your Meetings, in the Name and Power of the Lord, who was, and is, and is to come, who changeth not, as Times and Laws changeth. Be diligent in Meeting together; let none be idle, or come together in a careleſs indifferent mind, whether you come or not, for ſuch doth not ſerve the Lord as they ought faithfully, not are they ſenſible of the proſperity of his Work in them; and ſuch grow not in the Truth, Grace, or Knowledg of God; they ſhine not as Lights to the World or amongſt Men. But bleſſed and magnified be the Name of the Lord, that a remnant do walk with God and faithfully do his Will, who have not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed their Garments, but have kept them clean; who glorifie their Heavenly Father by bringing forth much Fruit to him; whom the Lord hath hid in the ſecret of his Pavillion, and he will hide them more and more in his munition'd Rock, whoſe Bread is ſure, and whoſe Waters never fails. In the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of the Cup of Salvation was I conſtrained at this time to write this Epiſtle to you, who are of the Flock of God, who will give you a Kingdom that is far beyond the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of this World; in which all that abide faithful to the end, ſhall live and reign with God the Father, and the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, for ever and ever; which that you all may be found Heirs thereof and come to inherit it, is the fervent Deſire and Prayer to God, of </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>your faithful Friend and Brother in the Truth, James Parke.</signed>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>Horſteydown</hi> 
                     <date>the 24th. of 5th. Month, 1687.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
